Emotional well-being plays an important role
in how we face new challenges,
and then learn and grow because of them.
But when it comes to managing our emotions,
sometimes we're literally stuck in the Stone Age.
According to evolutionary biology, we've changed
in many ways over thousands of years,
but our brain is still wired to perceive environmental threats
the same way our primitive ancestors did.
Our brain perceives danger nonetheless.
In fact, our modern-day brain tends to overreact
and lose focus when we sense danger.
And it doesn't differentiate all that well between survival threats
and more routine interpersonal conflicts.
When we feel positive and calm, we have more perspective
and are better able to assess
what is a real threat versus what is not.
We can learn from and overcome challenges,
and we're able to connect better with others.
Think about what it feels like when you are at your best,
learning and performing
and enjoying yourself in the process.
We can and should actively replicate this feeling
as often as we can.
When we are not feeling this way,
there are a number of ways we can engage and calm our brains
to bring us back to this zone of learning,
performance and enjoyment.
One of them is the practice of emotional flexibility.
Emotional flexibility starts with an awareness
of an emotion that isn't serving you.
Think about a time in the past few days
in which you experienced a negative emotion.
Maybe you were a little bothered by something,
or maybe you were actually closer to being angry.
But bring that moment to mind.
What are you feeling and thinking right now?
What were you feeling and thinking in the moment? And why?
Once you're aware, the next step
to emotional flexibility is counterintuitive.
Practice acceptance.
It turns out that trying to reject negative feelings
can actually make them stronger.
So imagine yourself back in that moment,
and allow yourself to feel however it is you're feeling.
There's a reason for it,
so you don't need to interrupt those emotions.
Instead, explore your feelings and get curious.
What does it feel like? Where does it affect you?
Does the feeling seem to have a color? A temperature?
You could try to visualize this emotion
that is not serving you.
You might even have some fun with it.
For example, here comes the blue octopus, my anxiety.
With that clear awareness of what's happening to you,
it's easier to recognize and accept the feeling.
Once you have accepted your feelings,
you can work through them more quickly by making an active choice.
You have two options.
Directly addressing what you're feeling,
or choosing to let it go.
For example, after a tough conversation with a colleague,
you might choose to follow up and to listen,
and understand more about their perspective.
Or to vulnerably share how it affected you.
You could also sit with it by yourself and consider…